Guide to the Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
- Series III. Correspondence to or from other Lavoisier's relatives or associates
  - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Paris, November 5, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Summary: Received his steam boiler but is disappointed not to have received the blades for his graters.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, je viens de recevoir ma / chaudiere en bon etat…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, November 13, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Summary: Hopes to receive the blades for his graters soon.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, j'éspere que l'auvergnat te tiendra parole…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, August 20, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      Summary: Orders supplies and describes the state of his sugar-refinery.
      Letter begins: "thierry se rendra à paris le 25, / je te prie, mon bon ami, delui / tenir prets 5 à 6 toneaux de noir..."
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, October 30, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Summary: Discusses Charlot's financial arrangement with Chaptal fils, orders ten barrels of bone black, and expresses satisfaction with changes he made in the production of sugar.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, ainsi que je te lavois / annoncé mr charlot vient de / fournir Sur toi un effet de 1000 + …"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, July 3, 1821 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Summary: Explains at length why he cannot support Mlle. Gervais's fermentation process.
      Letter begins: "j'ai recu, mon cher ami, le paquet et ta / lettre du 30…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, December 22 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Summary: Discusses his experiments with nitric acid and makes observations on the decomposition of acid by mercury for the production of corrosive sublimate and mercure doux."
      Letter begins: "voyla bien dutemps, mon cher ami, / que je n'ai reçu detes nouvelles…"
  - Chazelles, Augustin Jean-Baptiste de, comte
    - Chazelles Augustin Jean-Baptiste de, comte, [letter], [to Louis XVIII], June 22, 1821 (Box 43, Folder 28)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 21 cm
      Summary: As Prefect of the Morbihan, the Comte de Chazelles thanks the king for having given money for the poor of his département.
      Letter begins: "Monseigneur/Je reçois avec une vive reconnaissance la lettre que Votre Excellence m'a fait l'honneur de m'adresser le 18 de ce mois..."
  - Chazelles, Madame de
    - Chazelles, Madame de, Champaissant, [to] Maître Etienne Ader, February 21, 1956 (Box 43, Folder 30)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 27 cm; copy of a letter
      Summary: Confirms that the articles described in the auction sale catalog come from the heritage of Lavoisier's family.
      Letter begins: "Mon cher Maître/J'ai bien reçu le catalogue de la vente des Souvenirs de Lavoisier à laquelle vous devez procéder pour mon compte le 7 March prochain..."
  - Darcet, Jean
    - Darcet, Jean [to] Guillotin, Undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 12 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Forwards for a friend of Guillotin a recipe to improve the quality of wine and vinegar.
      Letter begins: "Je Souhaite bien le bonjour / au Citoien Guillotin et je lui / Envoie cy jointe la note…"
  - Dumas, Jean Baptiste André
    - Dumas, Jean Baptiste André [to] Monsieur Pingard, 1883 7bre 24 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Summary: Complains about a draft from a window over his desk and requests a double window.
      Letter begins: "Cher Monsieur Pingard / Voilà deux fois en un an / que la fenêtre placée au dessus..."
  - Dupont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel
    - Dupont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel [to] Citoyen Harmand, New York to Paris, February 24, 1801 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Summary: Describes his sea voyage and dwells at length on his unhappy relationship with Mme. Lavoisier (without naming her).
      Letter begins: "nº19 / non, mon cher Harmand, je ne t'enverrai point la / longue lettre que je t'ai écrite en mer…"
  - Fourcroy, Antoine François
    - Manuscripts and printed documents by or about Fourcroy, May 12, 1785-December 21, 1809 (Box 43, Folder 40)
      Physical Description: 8 items; 26 x 20 cm. or smaller
      Summary: Eight items from the collection of Denis Duveen. (a) Letter of thanks from Fourcroy to an unidentified count, May 12, 1785; (b) letter from Fourcroy to Citoyen Lacuée, Conseiller d'etat, 16 brumaire, an 9 de la République, recommending a Martial Floucaud for a position in the gendarmerie of the Département de la Coreze; (c) letter from Fourcroy to Citoyen Justin Lamoureux, thanking him for sending him a literary history of the Département de la Meurthe, 30 germinal, an 11 de la République; (d) printed announcement of Fourcroy's death, addressed to Madame Lignon [?], December 16, 1809; (e) printed invitation to Fourcroy's funeral, to be held on December 20, 1809; (f) manuscript of a eulogy given at Fourcroy's funeral by M. de Prony, with minor corrections, December 20, 1809; (g) manuscript account of Fourcroy's funeral, with text of the eulogies given by Regnaud de Saint-Jean d'Angély, Prony, and M. Thouret, followed by a memorial statement by the Faculté de Médecine de Paris, December 20-21, 1809; (h) manuscript, "Notes sur la conduite du C. Fourcroy dans la revolution," evidently by Fourcroy, undated.
      First item (a letter) begins: "On ne peut etre plus sensible que je l'ai été aux bontés que vous avez bien voulu ..."
    - Fourcroy, Antoine-François de, comte, [to] the Ministre de l'Intérieur [Jules François Paré], September 24, 1793 (Box 43, Folder 38)
      Summary: About the new premises of the Commission des Poids et Mesures.
      Letter begins: "Je vous adresse, Citoyen Ministre, le procès-verbal rédigé par les Commissaires des poids et mesures sur le choix du local..."
    - Fourcroy, Antoine François de, comte [to] Citoyen Fabien Pillet [Pittet?], Paris, September 20, 1802 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Physical Description: 1 sheet; 18 x 24 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Letterhead: "Conseil d'Etat." Requests that the theater "répertoires" be sent to Mme. Murat, Mme. Bonaparte, and to other relatives of the first consul.
      Letter begins: "J'invite le Citoyen fabien Pillet à envoyer les repertoires à…"
    - Fourcroy, Antoine François de, comte [to] Citoyen Coulomb, Paris, May 1, 1803 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Summary: Letterhead: "Le Conseiller d'Etat chargé de la Direction et de / la Surveillance de l'Instruction publique." Acknowledges the receipt of a letter and a package from the Minister of the Interior relating to Mailly.Général..."
      Letter begins: "au Citoyen Coulomb Secret.re g.al du Ministère / de l'intèrieur. / J'ai reçu hier au Soir, citoyen Secretaire…"
    - Fourcroy, Antoine François de, comte [to] Napoleon I, July 14, 1806 (Box 3, Folder 35a)
      Physical Description: 3 leaves; 34 cm; manuscript signed (photograph), original in the Archives nationales. Accompanied by a detailed letter of appeal to the Emperor (see Lavoisier MSS. 3.35b).
      Summary: Asks the Emperor to read their defense concerning the Lemercier affair.
      Letter begins: "A Sa Majesté / L'Empereur et Roi, / Sire, / Deux de vos plus fidèles sujets, deux membres / de votre institut…"
    - Fourcroy, Antoine François de, comte [to] Napoleon I, July 14, 1806 (Box 3, Folder 35b)
      Physical Description: 8 leaves; 34 cm; manuscript signed (photograph), original in the Archives nationales. Accompanied by a letter of introduction to the Emperor (see Lavoisier MSS. 3.35a).
      Summary: Present their case against Lemercier, the former manager of their company, who made business deals in the name of the association for his own profit.
      Letter begins: "Précis / pour mm.rs Fourcroy et Vauquelin / dans l'affaire de h.ri Lemercier et Comp.ie / Au commencement de l'an neuf…"
  - Guyton de Morveau, Louis Bernard, baron
    - Guyton de Morveau, Louis Bernard, baron [to an unnamed man], Dijon, August 28, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 24 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Discusses Achard's work on the forces of adhesion which he is translating and would like to send the translation to his correspondent for an opinion on the chemist's work.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / Le peu de tems et de santé que m'ont laissé…"
    - Guyton de Morveau, Louis Bernard, baron [to] Citoiens Ricard frères, négocians à Dijon, Paris, May 5, 1800 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Summary: Acknowledges receipt of a letter and a pension payment but questions the sum involved. Holograph note signed Mureau on p. [3] acknowledging receipt of the disputed sum.
      Letter begins: "j'ai recu, Citoiens, avec votre lettre du 8, L'effet que vous / avez payé…"
  - Haüy, René Just
    - Haüy, René Just [to] Monsieur de Bouzancourt, Paris to Mézières, July 17, 1786 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm; holograph signed. Broken seal attached.
      Summary: Gives a detailed analysis of the abbé Bardoux's manuscript of religious and literary anecdotes, criticizing the abbot for his style, content, and lack of delicacy in his selections.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur et cher ami. / En attendant les nouveaux details que vous me promettés au sujet de la / commission…"
  - La Caille, Nicolas Louis de
    - La Caille, Nicolas Louis de [to] Monsieur Grischow, Paris to Isle D'Oesel [Estonia], November 29, 1757 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Received his colleague's letter and promises to send him any astronomical observations which may be useful to Grischow's work on the pendulum and longitude. Note in different hand on p. [1]. "Monsieur / J'ai recu a mon retour à Paris ala mi-novembre..."
      Letter begins: "Reçue dans la Conference / Academique le 6 Fevrier 1758. "
  - Lagrange, Joseph Louis, comte
    - Lagrange, Joseph Louis, comte [to] Citoyen Delambre, Boiscommun, January 7, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. Holograph (in Haüy's hand) signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Advises Delambre of his exclusion from the "Commision des poids et mesures." "La Commission des poids et mesures / au Citoyen Delambre. / Citoyen. / La Commission des poids et mesures a chargé le / Citoyen Deprony…"
      Letter begins: "La Commission des poids et mesures / au Citoyen Delambre. / Citoyen. / La Commission des poids et mesures a chargé le / Citoyen Deprony…"
  - Lakanal, Joseph
    - Lakanal, Joseph [to] Monsieur Morand, Paris, Undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 19 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Makes an appointement with Morand so that they may visit a city magistrate.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur et honorable ami: / les publications sont faites, et c'est Mr. / Villemsens adjoint à la mairie…"
  - Lalande, Joseph Jerôme Le Français de
    - Lalande, Joseph Jerôme Le Français de [to] Citoyen Agasse, Paris, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Summary: Asks Agasse to change the Republican dating system he uses in his Moniteur to the Gregorian Calendar, because the latter is used internationally. Marginal notes in different hand on p. [1].
      Letter begins: "Sur le Calendrier / Citoyen redacteur jem'intéresse aumoniteur depuis / sa fondation…"
  - La Métherie, Jean Claude de
    - La Métherie, Jean Claude de [to] Monsieur de Luc, July 8, 1790 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. Holograph signed. Seal attached. Right margin of p. [3] torn with loss of text.
      Summary: Announces the publication of de Luc's letter and explains the delay in receipt of a journal for the library of the King of England.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / votre derniere lettre du 1 juillet m'est parvenue..."
    - La Métherie, Jean Claude de [to] Monsieur de Luc, Windsor, December 8, 1790 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 21 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Announces the dispatch of the latest issues of the Journal de physique and asks for information on prices for several geography books and a globe on behalf of de Volney.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / j'ai fait remettre des le mois passé chez M. audifret…"
    - La Métherie, Jean Claude de [to an unnamed man], Paris, August 28, 1802 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      Summary: Would like to continue their exchange of opinions on geological questions, and requests assistance for Mr. Maleszewski who intends to go to Poland.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / il y a longtems que nous ne nous sommes entretenus de geologie…"
    - La Métherie, Jean Claude de [to] Citoyen Gillet-Laumont, Paris, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 19 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Informs him that the Journal de physique has been sent to Lenoir and Mathieu although they have not renewed their subscription, and asks if it should still be sent to them.
      Letter begins: "j. c. de la metherie dit mille choses amicales / au citoyen gillet laumont…"
  - Laplace, Pierre Simon, marquis de
    - Laplace, Pierre Simon, marquis de [to] Citoyen Delambre, Paris, March 3, 1794 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 18 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Discusses at length Delambre's measurements of the parallels of Greenwich and Montjoui in order to determine the length of the meter.
      Letter begins: "j'ai reçu, Mon cher Confrêre, les resultats que vous avez / bien voulû m'envoyer, & je vous en fais mes remercimens…"
  - Macquer, Pierre Joseph
    - Macquer, Pierre Joseph [to] l'abbé Cotton des Houssayes, Paris, April 2, 1781 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. Holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Promises to visit the abbé when Macquer's chemistry classes begin at the "jardin du roi."
      Letter begins: "Pardon, Monsieur, Si j'ai differé a repondre / a la lettre don’t vous m'avez honoré le 14 mars…"
  - Méchain, Pierre François André
    - Méchain, Pierre François André [to] Monsieur Cotte, Paris to Montmorency, December 10, 1790 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Summary: Discusses various scientific matters including his involvement with the Connaissance des temps, meteorological observations, and tables of magnetic declination for the Dictionaire de physique.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur et Cher Confrere / La connoissance des tems pour 1792 ne paroit pas encore…"
    - Méchain, Pierre François André [to] Général Bournonville, Palme de Mayorque, March 28, 1804 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Summary: Asks that the Capitaine Général of the province of Valencia receive orders facilitating Méchain's operations in that area, and that L. Canellas be granted a salary for his research.
      Letter begins: "Méchain, de l'Institut national et du Bureau des Longitudes; / À Son Excellence le Général Bournonville, Ambassadeur de / la République Francaise prés Sa Majesté Catholique. / Général Ambassadeur, / En vous adressant..."
  - Monge, Gaspard, comte de Péluse
    - Monge, Gaspard, comte de Péluse [to] Général d'armée Berthier, Paris, December 1, 1801 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Summary: With vignette and letterhead: "Egalité. Liberté." Recommends two of the four men he interviewed for placements as "élèves des poudres et salpêtres."
      Letter begins: "Citoyen Ministre, / Vous m'avez chargé d'examiner les personnes qui concourent pour des places d'Eleves…"
  - Moreau, ____, marchand
    - Moreau, ____, marchand [to] Messieurs de L'Académie royale des sciences, Paris, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 33 cm; manuscript signed.
      Summary: Proposes a cheaper and more efficient way of street lighting. "Messieurs / Le Sr. Moreau Marchand Mercier rüe St. Martin / a l'honneur devous réprésenter, qu'il a trouvé le moyen /"
  - Norbat, ____
    - Norbat, ____ [to] the Académie royale des sciences, Paris, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Summary: As a foreign participant in the city-lighting contest, he appearls to the integrity and impartiality of the commission. "Messieurs / Si Un Citoyen Zelé a Sacrifié Milles Livres…"
  - Paulze, Jacques
    - Paulze, Jacques, Bescy, [to] Mme. de Beaumanoir, Paris, August 29, 1778 (Box 43, Folder 18)
      Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; letter autograph
      Summary: About the cultivation of French Guyana, clearing, climate problems. Describes the work of slaves, and the building of cabins to house them.
      Letter begins: "Je suis fort aise, Madame, que vous soiés contente de M. Pierre; je ne l'aurois pas proposé à la Compagnie, si je n'eusse été aussi assuré de ses talens..."
  - Peronnin, Pierre.
    - Peronnin, Pierre. [to] Fougeroux de Bondaroy?, Moulins en Bourbois, July 25, 1784 (Box 4, Folder 8a)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; holograph signed. Accompanied by eleven documents certifying Peronnin's credentials [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l)
      Summary: Sends models of agricultural tools he has invented and forwards a memoir and documents certifying the value of his inventions. "Monsieur, / Depuis que vous m'avés fait l'honneur de m'écrire pour m'annoncer que la société desiroit /"
    - Certificate recommending Perronin for his conduct and honesty, Paris written by Pannelier d'Annel, Pierre Lucien., January 5, 1779 (Box 4, Folder 8b)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 22 cm; manuscript signed.
      Summary: Number 1 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate recommending Perronin on the basis of his family, personality, and agricultural knowledge, Paris written by Blambuinon, ____, de, January 5, 1779 (Box 4, Folder 8c)
      Summary: Number 2 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate recommending Perronin for his personality and agricultural knowledge written by Moulins (France), November 10, 1783 (Box 4, Folder 8d)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; manuscript signed by municipal officials. Seal attached.
      Summary: Number 3 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions written by Coiffier, Jean Louis., December 3, 1783 (Box 4, Folder 8e)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; holograph signed. Seals attached.
      Summary: Number 4 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions, Moulins written by Vernin, Jacques., December 6, 1783 (Box 4, Folder 8f)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; manuscript signed. Seal Attached.
      Summary: Number 5 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions, Trevol written by [illegible signature], March 15, 1785 (Box 4, Folder 8g)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 28 cm; holograph signed. With additional signed recommendation on p. [4].
      Summary: Number 6 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions, Rocle written by Unknown, April 5, 1784 (Box 4, Folder 8h)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 31 cm; manuscript signed by village representatives.
      Summary: Number 7 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions, Monestier written by Bayon, ____, curé, April 17, 1784 (Box 4, Folder 8i)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; holograph signed. With additional certification and signatures of village representatives on p. [3], dated 18 April 1784.
      Summary: Number 8 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions, Montoldré written by Grillet, ____, curé, May 15, 1784 (Box 4, Folder 8j)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; holograph signed. Also signed by village representatives.
      Summary: Number 9 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate testifying to the success of Peronnin's agricultural inventions, Moulins written by Coiffier Deverfeux, François, June 2, 1784 (Box 4, Folder 8k)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Number 10 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
    - Certificate recommending Peronnin on the basis of his personality, devotion to his country, and agricultural inventions, Moulins written by Faulconnier, ____., July 20, 1784 (Box 4, Folder 8l)
      Summary: Number 11 of 11 recommendations [Lavoisier MSS. 4.08b-l]
  - Sage, Balthazar Georges
    - Sage, Balthazar Georges [to an unnamed man], Paris, July 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Summary: Encourages the addressee's nephew to visit and mix with the young students at the mines near Anzin and promises to recommend him to the minister.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / je viens d'apprendre, que les éleves des mines /"
    - Sage, Balthazar Georges [to] Le Mercier, Antoni, October 21 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 17 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Speaks at length of the ailments which he contracted during his imprisonment.
      Letter begins: "Citoyen / il y a deux mois et demi que j'ai quitté / paris…"
  - Sage, Madame.
    - Sage, Madame. [to] Monsieur Le Mercier, Paris, June 3, 1803 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 16 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Asks Le Mercier to come to discuss a matter concerning his daughter.
      Letter begins: "J'ai L'honner / de souhaiter le bonjour / à mes bons amis…"
  - Seguin, Armand
    - Seguin, Armand, [from], [Paris], [to] Monsieur de Jussieu, April 1, 1791 (Box 43, Folder 39)
      Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 24 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: About a communication of Seguin before the Académie des Sciences.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/Lorsque je vous ai prié de vouloir bien m'inscrire au nombre de ceux qui doivent lire deMayn des mémoires à l'Académie..."
  - Silvestre, Auguste François, baron de
    - Silvestre, Auguste François, baron de [to] Monsieur le duc de Feltre, Paris, December 18, 1810 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 35 cm; manuscript signed
      Summary: With vignette and letterhead: "Société d'agriculture du Département de la Seine." Sends 100 copies of a memoir by Collaine on the treatment of glanders and farcy, with the request to distrbute them among the military veterinarians. Note in a different hand on p. [1].
      Letter begins: "A Son Excellence, Monsieur / Le Duc de Feltre, Ministre de la Guerre. / Monseigneur, / J'ai l'honneur de vous adresser..."
  - Vauquelin, Louis Nicolas
    - Vauquelin, Louis Nicolas [to an unnamed man], Paris, May 25, 1823 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 26 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Acknolwedges receipt of a "mandat" to be paid by M. Laffite, and asks his correspondant to monitor one of Vauquelin's financial matters.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur, / Je profite de l'occasion de mon frère qui va passer / quelque temps en normandie…"
- Series IV. Lavoisier and associates' scientific notes and manuscripts
  - Lavoisier's notes and manuscripts
    - Memoir supplementing Lavoisier's work submitted to the Académie des sciences for the Paris streetlighting contest, 1766 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Physical Description: 6 leaves; 32 cm; manuscript